Stanford University all right so the
last time we were beginning to get to
the idea of a quantum field and that's
what I want to get to today what is a
quantum field I always it related to
particles we spent a little bit of time
talking about harmonic oscillators and
the basic mathematical tool for quantum
fields for any kind of fee twelve
quantum fields for any kind of quantum
fields is the harmonic oscillator and
putting how oscillators together to make
quantum fields so we talked about um
fields on a periodic space so I'm not
going to draw the periodic space the
periodic space is one which after you go
a distance L comes back to itself it's a
useful trick and the reason it's a
useful trick better than just taking a
finite line interval is because when you
have a periodic space you can have waves
which go in one direction always which
go in the other direction without
reflecting and that is the analog of
momentum Kyle it's not the analog it is
momentum conservation so if you want to
retain momentum conservation it's a good
idea if you want to maintain momentum
conservation and temporarily put a
system in a finite box so that you don't
have an infinite volume to worry about
then the right way to do it is periodic
boundary conditions and then under those
circumstances a wave a plane wave
instead of being sines and cosines will
be of the form e to the I KX our K can
be positive or negative
a K being positive corresponds to a wave
moving to the right round the loop okay
moving negative K corresponds to a
going the other direction just to remind
you K is not an arbitrary number it has
to be it has to come in integer
multiples of something or other in order
that the wave when it comes back to
itself after going around the distance L
that the wave comes back to its own
original value so if we say that X and
going all the ways around I said I
wouldn't draw it but I did the distance
around this L then e to the I K L must
be what it's got to be it's got to be
one it's got to be one at x equals zero
here's x equals zero right over here
this function is one when x equals zero
any exponential of X is one and when it
goes all the ways around better come
back to itself so that means that e to
the ikx
e to the let's say I KZ ro x equals zero
x equals L e to the IKr is just 1 and
what does that mean e to the i KL equals
1 what does that say that says that K
times L must be an integer multiple of 2
pi e to the 2 pi I is equal to 1 how do
I know that well we can just work it out
remember what the exponential means it
means cosine of 2 pi plus sorry 2 pi
plus I times sine 2 pi cosine of 2 pi is
1 sine is 2 pi is 0 and so indeed this
is equal to 1 and in fact if you put any
multiple of
my dear it's also one so as long as KL
is an integer multiple of 2 pi this is a
periodic function e to the ikx is a
periodic function so K times L must be
equal to 2 pi times an integer and let's
call that integer n this integer should
be distinguished from another in which
will occur later it's the end which
counts the number of quanta of each type
all right this is not counting the
number of quanta of particles it's just
counting the allowable wave numbers this
is called the wave number and um right
so K times L is 2 n PI or K must be 2 pi
in over L that's the that's the
condition on K that when you go around
the function comes back to itself so
that's why one thing incidentally this
is exactly the same thing as the
quantization of the wavelength saying
the wavelength has to fit in an integer
multiple of times by the time you come
back what's the connection between K and
wavelength yeah
the wavelength is inverse to ke there's
a 2pi in the relationship Ella yeah um
if we turn this over it's 1 over K
equals L divided by 2 pi n
or well you can work that out I'll let
you work that out this is this is the
condition on K it is equivalent to the
condition that the wavelength be
quantized so that it just fits into the
circle and integer number of times so
this is these are the kind of ways you
can have period periodically arm if we
are talking about the waves that are
associated with some quanta then K is
related to the momenta I guess we'd
better work that out I guess we better
work out the relation between K and the
wavelength um what is the wavelength
associated with a wave like this well
it's the distance you have to move
before I eat to the AYGO K goes through
one full cycle so if I want to find out
the wave length of an object like this
the wavelength of this kind of wave I
just say that that K times X or K times
the wavelength has to be K times the
wavelength wavelength lambda has to be 2
pi or K is the same thing as 2 pi
divided by the wavelength so that's the
relation between K and wavelength when
wavelength is big K is small when
wavelength is small K is big and there's
a 2pi relating them but they're closely
related alright so that's the relation
between K and wavelength does anybody
remember the relationship between the
wavelength of a photon or anything else
and its momentum right momentum of a
particle we're making a bunch of
connections momentum of a particle
described by a given quantum mechanical
wave the momentum of a particle is equal
also to what h-bar where H divided by
lambda is that right
hmm yeah H over lambda but I can express
that in terms of H bar and then there
would be a 2 pi H bar over lambda so you
can see that up that P and K are
essentially the same thing except for a
factor of K sorry except for a fact of H
bar all right in particular momentum is
H bar times K so if I have a wave
described this is called the wave number
K is called the wave number if the wave
number and it can be positive or
negative waves moving to the left moving
to the right
corresponding to momenta going to the
left or the right so that's the basic
that's the basic wave on a circle if you
like or wave on a periodic space now for
each such kind of wave there can be
quanta quanta corresponding to particles
how do we describe that those those
quanta well we just will just describe
the number of quanta with momentum P or
equivalently the number of quanta with a
given wave number K are many quanta are
there with a given wave number K since K
is itself an integer we have to specify
an integer for each integer one of those
integers is just related to the wave
number the other integer is called the
occupation number the number of quanta
occupying that particular wave if you
like or that particular wavelength
alright so there are ins which
correspond to the quantization of
momentum but there are also ins
which correspond to the
to the number of quanta with each
momentum those are called
occupation numbers so I could write and
I will write n of K this is a different
end now n of K K is itself quantized but
in of K is the number of particles or
the number of quanta with wave number K
which in effect means with momentum P
but just remember there is a relay that
P and K happen to be related by h-bar of
course if I'm smart I choose a units in
which cable K is equal to 1 knot K is
equal to 1 H bar is equal to 1 and then
key and P are the same thing so we often
don't even bother to distinguish between
wave number and momentum we speak of K
as the momentum of the particle and K
positive yeah so you have a collection
of occupation numbers for every value of
K including negative and positive
numbers ok yeah Michael yeah hey
okay is not itself an integer wave
number is not an integer that's correct
K is two PI over L times an integer but
this integer is not the occupation
number okay we could I don't know what a
I don't know any other good notation for
integer except in unfortunately and so
everything which is quantized winds up
being called n except when it's L but I
don't want to call this thing L because
it's not L what does L L is angular
momentum which is also quantized so we
got to keep track of the two different
kinds of integers one of them the
discrete momentum and the other the
discrete number of quanta with each
momentum and the way to keep track of it
is occupation numbers I will call n of K
meaning the number of quanta with
momentum K K itself is also quantized
okay all right so occupation number
number of particles with a given
momentum k next we introduce operators
quantum mechanical operators for those
who know a little bit of quantum
mechanics you will remember that state
vectors are linear what's what should we
call them state vectors I will shoot
anybody who calls them vectors state
vectors because we will get them
confused with the directions in space
linear elements let's just call them
linear elements elements they are
elements of a vector space but they
forget to forget that the state vectors
of a system are linear elements that we
can add and so forth but we can also
operate on them with operators we've
gone through this
at least twice in this clan in this
series of classes and um the observables
of a quantum mechanical system are the
hermitian or real valued operators which
operate on the state's operate means
they are operations which change a state
into another state now what is the state
what is it what is a convenient way to
label the possible states of a system of
quanta moving on such a circle is to
specify all the end of K so you can
think of it as in one and of one and of
two with one two and so forth refer to
the values of K and of three or I should
also I also have to put an end of - 1 -
2 don't I well darn it how am I going to
do this I just have to imagine that this
string is the string goes by both to the
left end to the right and that
represents a state with n1 quanta with
the first value momentum into quanta
with the second value momentum we're not
to specify with these values of K are
just the first one second one third one
and so forth the - one - tooth so that's
a quantum state of the quanta moving on
the circle and now there are operators
analogous to not only analogous to but
really equivalent to are the harmonic
oscillator creation and annihilation
operators the raising and lowering
operators remember the harmonic
oscillator
is described by operators a plus and a
minus
I'm not multiplying now I'm just writing
them a plus in my a minus a plus
increases these are the energy levels of
the oscillator it increases takes you
from zero quanta to one quanta one
quanta the two quanta and so forth and
so on and a minus takes you back down
okay so what these operators are and
there's one of them for each momentum
are one a plus and one may a minus for
each momentum so they should be labeled
as a plus of K and a minus of K so what
does a plus of K do when it acts on a
state vector like this well it goes to
the k DH slot for example let's take a
plus of one it goes to the first slot
here and increases the number of quanta
by one unit it also does something else
you remember what the other thing it
does it multiplies by something square
root of n square root of n plus 1 hmm
yeah yeah
for the minus is just square root of n
right so I'll remind you to keep track
of those coefficients that are explained
last time and as a bookkeeping device
it's a bookkeeping device the a plus is
the the square roots alright so a plus
of 1 and in general a plus of K goes to
the caithe momentum slot I really should
call it a plus maybe of n of K where
that's going to get no no no no no
that's bad that's bad nah no just a plus
of K increases the number of quanta with
momentum K by 1 unit
and a - decreases it at the same time
multiplying by the appropriate square
root of n all right those are that's the
that's set of mathematical objects that
we have to deal with and how do we build
a quantum field what is the connection
between the quantum field and the
a-pluses in the a - is well I'll tell
you now little secret what the a pluses
in the a minuses are in another language
they're the quantum mechanical versions
of the Fourier coefficients the Fourier
coefficients of the field a field on a
periodic circle like this can be
represented let's go let's give the feel
the name let's call it Sai let's call it
Sai and Sai is a field it's a function
of X and any such field on a periodic
interval like that can be represented as
an infinite sum over the allowable
values of ke I write sum over K you say
what values of K a my summing over I'm
summing over the allowable values of K
of what coefficients let's call them
alpha of K e to the I K X that's the
same as expanding it in sines and
cosines at psy and there is another
object size star once our star
the complex conjugate of sorry obviously
psy is a in general a complex thing e to
the ikx is a complex thing if psy is a
complex thing it has a real and
imaginary part the real part plus I
times the imaginary part is psy real
part minus I times the imaginary part is
called the complex conjugate that's
equal to the sum on K of the complex
conjugate of Alpha times
what's the complex conjugate of e to the
ikx e to the minus ikx so to specify a
classical wave let's call this a
classical wave you specify all of these
Fourier coefficients these Fourier
coefficients you don't have to specify
separately the alphas in the Alpha stars
if you know alpha you know alpha star
but you do have to specify the real and
imaginary part of the alphas okay so a
classical configuration of a wave is
specified by giving the alphas the
quantum mechanical a pluses in a minuses
are the quantum mechanical versions of
the alphas these are observables why are
they observables because if you have a
wave you can measure the amplitude of
each of its Fourier components this is
the amplitudes of the Fourier components
can you measure them sure so their
observables or at least the real and
imaginary parts of them are observables
classically if you can measure the real
part and the imaginary part the whole
thing is observable but strictly
speaking when you do an observation you
get a real number so an alpha really
stands for two observables a real and
imaginary part on
the quantum mechanical version of the
alphas I'm not going to write equals
that wouldn't quite make sense these are
classical variables these are quantum
mechanical operators but instead of
writing equals let's write them I don't
know sort of equals that means
approximately equal yeah yeah back and
forth arrow that means in quantum in
quantizing the system you replace alpha
by A's so the double arrow means replace
body the same thing here alpha star yeah
do I have this right I wonder if I have
it I wonder if um I think I have it
right as we go along let me decide to
change the definition so that this is
called alpha star and that's alpha it's
not important because you you have the
freedom let's say yep I'm going to
change it you have a standard definition
and this is a convention of course if
alpha star is the congregate the outer
come up the conjugate of alpha alpha is
the conjugate of alpha star so there's a
matter of definition here that you can
choose either way but I think it's
standard if I remember to make this
identification again it's not terribly
important then you say the quantum field
the definition of the quantum field is
simply replace the alphas by the create
Shanaya Latian operators a marinus of K
a plus of K now of course of K of course
we would have to prove that in some
sense or another the classical alphas in
some appropriate limit the A's must
behave like the alphas in what sense I
can just make this replacement there on
the blackboard but you probably say to
yourself why is that the right
replacement and what since the these
quantum mechanical objects behave
anything like our like the classical
Fourier coefficients okay well in many
ways but them let's to see that we have
to go a little more into the dynamics of
quantum fields and we will we will a
little bit but let's just take it as a
matter of definition now that a quantum
field is represented as a fourier some
where the fourier coefficients are
operators that makes sense that the
fourier coefficients are operators that
make sense because a fourier
coefficients you expect to be
observables and that the structure of
those observables or the relation
between them is exactly the relation
between creation and annihilation
operators the field is now the field is
an operator right yep
and change the star and make it
hermitian conjugate
after 19 question no so my understanding
was that when quantum field theory
introduced a major breakthrough was that
it allowed for particle creation
annihilation and you use the terms
dilation creation rod that doesn't mean
that the dynamics will create an
Annihilator articles for that we have to
go into the make the dynamics of these
fields well they change the number of
particles what the A's and the a pluses
in the a minuses do is they change the
number of particles these things here
represent the number of particles with
momentum one number of particles of
momentum two number of particles of
momentum three and what the A's do is
they change now to say that the A's
change the number of particles doesn't
mean that nature goes around changing
the number of particles these are
mathematical symbols which change the
number of particles it doesn't mean that
particle number changes okay that is it
that's a matter of laws of nature where
the laws of nature permit the number of
particles to change but if the number if
the laws of nature do allow the number
of particles to change these operators
are going to be very useful in
describing those kind of changes now
there's other situations even where the
number of particles doesn't change
well it looks let's look at this let's
look at what we can do with these
operators um supposing we want to
describe a reaction where a particle
scatters a particle scatters when it
scatters let's say we have one particle
not a whole bunch of particles one
particle of a given momentum K and that
particle is going to scatter collide
with something and it's going to come
off
with another momentum how do we describe
how how might we describe such a process
we might describe a process like that by
saying let's start with the state with
one particle where shall I put that
particle in here
whatever the momentum of the particle
happens to be if the particle happens to
have momentum k7 then I will make a 0 0
I'll go to the seventh place and put a 1
there and then 0 0 0 that's supposed to
be the seventh place ok so this
describes a state with one particle of
momentum k7 whatever k7 happens to be
now I want to describe a process where
the particle of a given momentum
scatters and comes off with some
different momentum now so far we've only
been talking about one dimension of
motion we've been talking about motion
on a line ok we can do motion on a line
and we can even think of changes of
momentum a particle gets hit by
something and it's momentum changes how
can we describe that well we can
describe that by saying we can describe
that by an operator which makes exactly
those changes namely take an operator
which removes this particle what's that
that's a minus of 7
okay or a minus of K sub 7 but the a
minus of 7 that removes that particle
and then puts back another particle in
another momentum state for example if
it's a scattering where a particle goes
from momentum k 7 to k9 then we'll put
here a plus of 9:00 okay 9:00
maybe I should call it let's call it K
let's let's let's write it that way a
minus of K seven a plus of k 9 what does
this do
it acts on a state with a momentum with
K 7 and switches it the k-9 so it's a
scattering it's a kind of scattering
process or it does it does what the
scattering process well here here it
doesn't matter here the that just
multiplies by war that you operators you
have a scalar multiplier so resent
square we said into something square
root of n 7
but then 7 is 1 right then having right
so let's see what this does it first
removes this particle with a coefficient
1 so it gives a plus of K 9 times 0 0 0
0 0 0 what's what is the state called
with all zeros called the vacuum alright
so when I speak of the vacuum it is also
the ground state and also the state of
lowest energy and in this simple example
we could call it the vacuum meaning no
particles all right so the first
operator takes a state it makes the
vacuum out of it and then the second
operator comes now the creation operator
multiplies by square root of n plus 1
right all right but we go then to k9 k9
is out here its occupation number zero
so the n plus 1 is just going to give us
1 again
all right so this operation then gives
us zero zero zero zero but then out at
the ninth place it gives us a 1 so all
it's done with coefficient one is it's
switched the place where the particle is
from one momentum to another momentum
now there are if there are situations
where these square roots of n come in
and we'll talk about them we'll talk
about what they do they are important
but in this particular problem because
there was never more than one particle
in the problem it the square roots of n
don't do anything ok so here's an
example then where a scattering process
is described by a certain combination of
A's now let's let's go a little bit
further let's suppose that the laws of
physics allow for the possibility that
the number of particles is not conserved
okay
supposing one particle can come in and
two particles can go out oh this process
of course we could have described in
another way we didn't need to go to this
arm complicated story with occupation
numbers we could have just said a
particle makes a transition from one
momentum to another but now let's get a
little fancier and say the laws of
physics permit a new kind of process
where the number of particles change for
example one particle comes in it might
collide with something and two particles
of the same kind go out but two
particles with different momenta
particle of K one comes in and two
particles one of K three and one of K
five go out don't worry too much about
momentum conservation I'm assuming
there's something to soak up the recoil
some other object how would we describe
that
that would be difficult to describe in
one particle quantum mechanics one
particle quantum mechanics means the
quantum mechanics of a single particle
this was this is possible to describe it
was never more than one particle 1
particle went to one particle but one
particle goes to 2 particles that you
can't describe in single particle
quantum mechanics but you can describe
it here again you remove ok the seventh
particle and you put in the ninth
particle and you also put in the
eleventh particle I don't know why I'm
taking only odd numbers let's put it an
even number a plus of 16 of K 16 so this
is a process where a particle of
momentum K 7 comes in may collide with
something one might say that that
something absorbs the particles just
language this is language the target
whatever it was absorbed this particle
and emitted two particles one of K 9 and
one of K 16 so this gives you
flexibility this the existence of these
operators and this space of states in
which the number of particles is
variable that gives you flexibility in
studying processes with a particle
number can change people cooking number
there
chocolate chip operator all right so if
a + creates a particle of momentum K a +
of K what does psy of X do sine of X is
also an operator it's a sum of operators
or let's take side dagger side dagger is
made up out of creation operators it
creates a particle of momentum K no
sorry 8 + create some particle of
momentum K what does I do so to
understand that you have to remember
that in quantum mechanics unlike
classical mechanics you get to add
States States form a linear I'm going to
say at a linear vector space that only
means that you can add them subtract
them and multiply them by ordinary
numbers all right so let's start with
the vacuum I'll just I'm not going to
write a string of zeros Oh stand for
oh-oh-oh-oh-oh-oh
okay and now we act with side dagger
first of what a side do incidentally
side tries to annihilate a particle but
there's no particle led to annihilate so
it just gives you zero no state at all
but let's take the creation of the
creation object side plus and act on
this I all we have to do now is follow
our nose sy plus of X where X is some
particular core value of position some
specific value of position let's see
what it does
yeah sigh dagger well we just substitute
the sigh we're at some of a K of a + of
K Oh times e to the I KX minus ikx but
what is this object here this is an
object which just represents one
particle with momentum K I didn't take
it outside
good point some e to the minus ikx
this is a one particle state with
momentum K what happens if i superpose
one-particle states with momentum k with
a set of coefficients e to the minus ikx
does anybody remember from quantum
mechanics what happens if you superpose
or add up state vectors corresponding to
a particle of momentum K and you add
them up with coefficience e to the minus
ikx
anybody remember no kazar momentum
states you got the right idea but you
wanted to
hmm these are momentum states this is a
momentum state what happens if you thin
doesn't take the operator this is a
momentum state we if we were doing one
particle quantum mechanics we might just
call this a particle of momentum ke one
particle alright in this in this problem
here I never have more than one particle
I act with this operator it gives me a
superposition of one particle States
each state that appears here is a one
particle state and it's a one particle
state with momentum K and I'm told to
add them up with e to the minus ikx it's
a position state it's a state with a
definite position what's the position X
right if you add up momentum states
within e to the ikx that gives you a
position stay as state located at
position X that's one particle quantum
mechanics so that tells us then what
side dagger of X does side dagger of X
creates a particle at position X it
creates a sum of particles it creates a
coherent quantum mechanical
superposition of States with momentum
momentum all the allowed momenta all
with coefficient e to the minus ikx
incidentally what's the probability for
different values of K
all the different values of K have the
same probability because the coefficient
here when squared all give one so this
is a linear superposition of states with
different momenta where the probability
remember what the probability is the
probability would just be the square of
this the square of this tile or it times
its complex conjugate this would be just
a state with a uniform probability in
momentum space all right but it is a
state with a definite with a particle at
a definite position okay so this is
getting pretty now sigh and the a pluses
of K and a minuses of K which are the
Fourier which ought to be interpreted as
the Fourier decomposition of psy of X
those are creation and annihilation
operators for particles with definite
momentum sigh of X and side Eiger of X
are creation and annihilation operators
for particles of definite position so if
you wanted to create a particle at
position X you would not do it with a of
K but you would do it instead with side
dagger of X which you can rewrite in
terms of A's of K but it's just giving
you the quantum mechanical superposition
of momentum states that adds up to a
position state okay that's the basic
idea of a quantum field uh when once the
in relativity it's a little more
complicated but if we don't worry about
the complications of a special theory of
relativity don't worry about them yet
then the quantum field side dagger of X
is a creation operator for a particle at
position
yeah in this case in this case this
spawn it it is a spot on that circle
yeah it's a spot on that circle now
eventually right eventually we can make
the circle bigger and bigger and bigger
what does that do
remember the allowable values of K were
2 pi integer over L okay so they're
spaced they're spaced by a spacing 2 PI
over L that's the spacing as L gets
bigger and bigger the spacing gets
smaller and smaller and eventually you
can have essentially any value of K or
at least for any value of K there's a
state arbitrarily close by so making
making the ring bigger and bigger and
bigger is equivalent to replacing the
discrete values of the momenta by
continuous values and what does that
entail for an equation like this right
it means that you integrate over K
instead of summing over K but it's good
the first time around to think about it
discreetly once you know when you
understand that you can replace it by
integral DK but let's not do that yet ok
next step next question what if sy
creates a particle at position X
obviously side dagger no no I take the
packet side agar creates a particle at
position X what does sy do
annihilates a particle at X right okay
let's think let's think now about the
possible kinds of reactions reactions I
now mean particle reactions that we
could think about but in the language of
sigh of X let's let's here's a possible
reaction you tell me if this is if you
think this is a likely thing a particle
comes in and when it hits a target where
the target happens to be localized very
precisely localized at position X that
particle disappears and then off on
Alpha Centauri somewhere as a particle
goes off here you know and somewhere is
on Betelgeuse another one goes off over
here that sound likely doesn't sound
likely it's what we would call non-local
it violates the rules that that signals
can propagate the arbitrary kind of
crazy velocities what what's the right
thing to think about the right thing to
think about if you want to preserve in
your theory very precise notion of
locality is that up off particle is
absorbed right over here and then two
particles are emitted the emitted
particles will be absorbed will be
emitted from the same spot now you might
want to loosen that up a little bit for
one reason or another and say well maybe
it only means if they were but they're
admitted within a certain region of that
but in fact the precise notion of
locality in quantum field theory is that
when a reaction happens it happens very
much at a spot like this so how would we
describe this reaction one particle
comes in is absorbed at X two particles
go out are emitted from the same point
we could use these operators to describe
more non-local processes but if we want
this local process what do we write we
write that a particle that the first
thing that happens is a particle is
removed from the system that's I at
point X and then two particles are put
back in at position X that would be side
dagger of X side dagger of X that might
act on a state with some sorry not not
the vacuum state but a state with
someone put with a particle in it
anything with some particle in it let's
try to figure out here's the exercise a
particle with momentum K comes in I want
to know if that particle with momentum K
is absorbed at position X what is the
final state what is the final state and
what is the various probabilities for
this final state to have this or that
momentum so what we have to do is very
simple in fact we have to first of all
say there's a particle with momentum K
here that means 0 0 0 and in the case
slot there's one particle that's the
first step write down the initial state
step number one step number two
substitute for these local these are
called local field operators because
they're localized at a position
substitute their expression if we're
trying to find out information about
momentum substitute in their expression
in terms of
momentum creation and annihilation
operators so let's do that okay so I of
X first of all is sum over K and again
some of it K means sum over the
allowable values of K a minus of K e to
the I K X that's sine of X what x do I
put in here the X at which the reaction
is happening all right so what kind of
what kind of action could we imagine can
you give me an example that would make
some sense well let's not talk
abstractly let's talk concretely
yeah we could have okay so then we will
have to have operators describing
different kinds of particles right no
but I mean you you've got the right idea
but let's use photons now this is not
quite the right description of photons
but let's ignore the photons are
relativistic particles this is more
appropriate than nonrelativistic
particles that's it let's ignore that
all right so a photon comes in hits an
atom localized at a point and from that
point two photons go off okay all right
so the first photon is the first is the
photon which we put into the system to
begin with what what comes next
all right so we take this field operator
that's the field operator which absorbs
a particle at position X and we allow it
to strike this initial state zero blah
blah blah one zero zero zero in the case
in the K place over here now this is a
sum of K this K is different than this K
and one what sense is this caitiff
this K here was summing this is a dummy
index just a summation index this is
some definite K let's call it K initial
the initial momentum of the particle
okay but our that that's the first step
then once we work that out we'll have to
hit it with side dagger of x times side
dagger of X and here's side dagger of X
so let's write that down since K is a
summation index we should use a
different letter we shouldn't use K over
again let's call it L these are
summation variables doesn't matter what
you call them I just don't want to
repeat the use of a summation variable
over here and call it the same thing
again so we have summation for the first
operator summation over L a plus of L e
to the I L X that's this are e to the
minus re election and what about the
second application of sigh of side
dagger we just have to write the same
thing again but again we better use a
different summation index because we're
not allowed to repeat the use of a
summation index twice that wouldn't make
sense we would mean so we have to repeat
same thing what should we call the new
summation index K L M our em doesn't
mean nasiha all rights wave number M a
plus of L e to the minus i ôm sorry m e
to the I minus I MX
all right what kind of state does this
create let's see what kind of state it
creates first of all here's a big sum
which terms of this sum give something
which is not equal to zero what case of
I only if this K here is not the same as
this K for example if this is K sub
thirteen that corresponds to the
thirteenth slot then what happens when I
apply K 1 e to the minus I K 1 well it
tries to absorb the first particle but
there is no first particle same for the
second once and only the 13th slot is
occupied so only K sub 13 will survive
or a sub 13 will survive when it hits
the state the rule is an annihilation
operator has to find something to
annihilate so this really reduces to one
term its summation not science not
summation one term and it's the term
with a minus of K 13 ok initial just K
initial K initial times e to the I K
initial X acting on this state 1 now
what does this do what does the
annihilation operator do when it hits
the state it just removes that particle
with a coefficient of 1 so it just we
just erase it and erase the particle and
all that's left is a state with no
particles times e to the I K in itial X
but now we have to apply this we have to
create particles
summation L well just be exactly the
summation that we have here this part of
it were finished with and it just gave
us an e to the I K initial x times the
vacuum okay now what do these do what
does this one do first it puts in a
particle of momentum L okay so it puts
in a particle of momentum L that's what
each other that's what a plus of L does
and what does this one do it puts in a
particle of momentum M so the whole
thing in the end is we keep that e to
the I Kayne itial X e to the minus I MX
e to the minus I LX x 0 0 but now when 1
0 0 1 0 whatever summed over Ln M which
ones which two sites are occupied ln m
ln m so what it's given me there's a sum
over ln m and now let's just replace
this let's just call this a two particle
state with a particle of momentum L and
a particle of momentum in the notation
is now I've used a different notation
I'm labeling this now as two particles
one with momentum L and one moment 'm m
and it's a sum over such states the sum
has not gone away but it's a sum over L
and M
with a coefficient with with a with a
functional dependence e to the I k1 X
minus MX minus LX all together summon ml
e to the I K in the show minus M minus L
x times L M yeah yeah the two creation
operators commute creation operators
commute okay that's a very good question
the rule is all creation operators
commute with each other all annihilation
operators commute with each other and
creation and annihilation operators
commute if they refer to different
momenta okay if they refer to if they
refer to the same momenta then they
don't commute
sit again ah for the speck good good
point good good good
okay right this is correct if M does not
equal L what is this this is what is the
probability for different values of L
and M coming from here no no no no
conservation momentum here because the
atom which absorbs the photon could
recoil right so the heavy atom could
absorb any amount of momentum all right
so there's no conservation of momentum
what this is up here is the change in
momentum initial momentum minus final
momentum it is of course the end the
momentum carried away by the atom all
right but this function here which is a
function of M and L is just a phase it's
magnitude is 1 so that means there are
equal probabilities for all values of L
and M when you square it the the wave
the you can think of this as the wave
function for a two particle State the
wave function is a pure phase and all
values of the momenta have equal
probability okay except not quite what
about if l equals m then i made a
mistake and the reason that I made a
mistake is when all right so let's go to
that particular case let's take one
particular case where L and M are the
same of course there are many many such
cases L could be a M could be anything
but I want to focus on those
contributions where the two where the L
and the M are the same alright this is
going to be the senator the factor e to
the 2i m
X on e to the minus 2i MX that's just
because L and M are the same so they'll
be the same factor of the same kind of
factor there but one thing will be new
what is it what happens when a plus ax
the first time
it gives me it gives me a particle and
the emphasize what happens if a plus ax
again no no it has the same momentum it
creates another particle but it gives me
a square root of 2 right it gives me a
square root of 2 after the first one
acted now I take the second one it looks
for a particle of momentum N and it
finds one damn it it finds one so
there's one particle present already
remember the rule is that if it finds n
particles here you give it a square root
of n square root of n plus 1 square root
of n plus 1 so what's the square root of
n plus 1 square root of 2
they have to be off by impossible LLL be
off by one no because I made it
impossible one worker if the a + n if
you're straight n plus 1 n plus don't
confuse particle number with momentum
number right right okay right so right
so for the special case where L and M
with the two particles come out with the
same momentum does it it could be that
momentum it could be that momentum it
could be that momentum if they come out
with the same momentum there's a factor
of square root of 2 what does it mean
about probabilities ya u square u square
these you square the coefficients of the
state vectors to find probability that's
odd if two particles go off in arbitrary
directions not the same with different
momenta or different momenta different
magnitudes of momenta there's one value
of the probability but if you produce
two particles with the same momentum
then the probability is twice as large
these particles like to be in the same
state these are in oh these are sorry
these are this is the description of
indistinguishable particles right this
is very much that this is the
description of particles which are not
distinguishable from each other so the
production of two photons in a collision
is twice as probable if the two photons
come off in the same state as if they
came off in different states
it tooks about the operators you're in a
complex we are but if you got in titled
economics and particles being generated
is it obvious
oh no it's not obvious what order but
with different orders you can always
commute them until they come out in the
order in which all the annihilation
operators are to the right and all the
creation operators up to the left that's
called normal ordering and in that
ordering the first thing you do is you
let the operators eat particles and then
spit out some new ones so normal
ordering but we'll come to that our old
saying there is like zero or bird s
person what's twice that okay that that
that is a good question but for that I
ask you to keep in mind the example in
which the moment' are quantized
for example the mud these could be
photons in a in a cavity where the
momenta really are quantized okay so if
if a particle and a cavity where the
momenta are quantized of a particle
photon comes in hits an atom and creates
two photons it will be twice as probable
for the two photons to be in the same
discrete energy level as to be in
different levels
it seems to me that there's there's only
one case where L equals M equals three
so here only one case that comes up in
the Sun where L equals M equals three
but there are two cases where one of L
and M is 2 and the other is 3 in other
words it LM are different then they show
up twice in the Sun okay so what let's
see um yeah you're right so let's see
what that says let's see
if L and M are different okay good good
good so let's do that case that's going
to give you a what kind of factor then
right you want your right so let's see
so what so if we have a of - a dagger of
- a dagger of three we have to add to
that plus a dagger of three a dagger of
- that's true so it looks like this one
is more probable but it's not as much
more probable as it would be if that
square root of two was with that so
let's okay so let me give you another
example where you really see this is
yeah I actually think you're right that
the that the ones with different
momentum because there are two different
ways to do it maybe more probable but
let me give you another example where
you can see the square roots of N in
action supposing we have a particle
which can decay so we have some sort of
particle which can decay and emit a
photon how do we describe that we
typically describe that by just one a
sigh of X suppose it can emit one photo
now let's see what yeah one photon one
photon is enough one photon is enough
all we want to do is create a photon at
point x let's create a photon at point X
all right so that's just side dagger of
X
acting on the vacuum this would be that
the K of an object producing a photon or
just the emission of a photon from a
point X what does this give this gives
some over momenta K creation operator of
momentum K e to the minus a plus e to
the minus I KX acting on the vacuum
vacuum means the state with no photons
in it for example all right what does
this give this gives the sum over K e to
the minus I KX times a state with a
particle of momentum K obviously equal
probability for all possible momenta k
in this particular case okay
equal probability for all moment the k
now let me do something else let me
suppose that there was pre-existing a
particle of momentum l that was
pre-existing in the cavity there was a
particle of momentum l and our atom
decays as an atom it's going to decay in
emitted photon but there's already a
pre-existing photon of momentum L the
first calculation told us that in the
simple model situation we have equal
probabilities for the emission of all
possible moment' that don't worry about
conservation laws here we've abandoned
them a while back tells us that there's
nothing distinctive about any of the
moment' that they all have equal
probabilities of being emitted but now
let's suppose there's already a
pre-existing particle of momentum L then
that means we have to operate on this
here with a particle that already has
momentum L in it there's a one here
someplace
okay supposing K is not this is the elf
place over here
supposing K is not equal to L then this
just creates a particle of momentum K
with no square roots of anything because
it looked for it created a particle of K
where there was no particle of ke
so the square root of n is just square
root of 1 and what does it do it creates
a state with an e to the minus ikx times
K and L the else particle is still there
and the new particle is K but now
supposing we look for the term in this
sum where K is equal to L then what do
we get then we get a square root of 2
then we get a square root of 2 so this
is correct as long as K is not equal to
L we get a state with two particles with
a wave function e to the minus ikx the
original elf particle is still Leia was
just a bystander and a particle of
momentum K was emitted it was emitted
with an amplitude e to the minus ikx a
quantum mechanical amplitude e to the
minus ikx
but what about the possibility that K
here is equal to L then what happens
by a factor of two by a factor of two
because now this a of K is a of L that
term is just a of L there's already a
particle there of momentum L and so you
get square root of 2 that's what these
operators do that's what these things do
they give you fact as the square root of
the number of particles of the type each
time one of these things acts so if
there was particles all over the place
here then you would have an enhanced
probability for producing particles of a
kind which already there yes that's
called that's called yes this is called
stimulated emission stimulated the did
particle l has to be is the same
location already this if you have a same
momentum in this case under the same
okay can't you both in the same position
and Z so it can be like yellow one mile
away
well really particles come out in wave
packets they don't really come out in
the street our momentum eigenstates but
in a cavity in a cavity they come out
with definite momenta and and this is a
real effect this is a real effect that
if there are particles present of
filling the cavity then the decay will
preferentially happen in two photons
which which have the momentum of the
particles in the cavity the more
particles you have in the cavity of a
given momentum the more probable it is
that the next particle will come out
with that momentum so if instead of
having one particle in this else slot we
had a hundred particles in this l slot
then we would get a factor of square
root of 101 I guess yeah square root of
and the probability would be 101 times
larger that the atom decays into the
state photon with the same momentum is
that 101 particles okay so you can
figure out more generally what the
answer will be
that's called stimulated emission and
what it means is that just the presence
of particles of a given type will
increase the probability that our decay
takes place but only when the decay
takes place with the final momentum
being the same little bit earlier so so
I gather the two new particles is still
preferred a different
yeah but not as a run but not as much as
if that extra square root too wasn't
there but then they will be attracted to
yeah it's not a real legitimate
attraction of any kind it's a
statistical effect it's there it's the
effect of identity identity of particles
now particles not all particles have
this same tendency incidentally
particles come in two kinds there are
fermions and bosons bosons are particles
described as I described them here
creation and annihilation operators with
the mathematics of the creation and
annihilation operators being the
mathematics of harmonic oscillators
particular square roots of n with the
creation and annihilation operators
having the algebraic commutation
relations of harmonic oscillators ah
then you have this tendency this is very
very general tendency that the more
particles you have the more likely it is
you will decay or produce particles of
the same momentum same thing happens in
scattering reactions if you have a
scattering reaction and it then it tends
to make particles of different momenta
if you already have moment' the present
of a certain kind it will tend to
preferentially cause the products of
collision to come out with the momentum
of the particles there incidentally I
said it's called stimulated emission
when a particle when a atom decays in
the presence of already pre-existing
photons that enhances the probability
for it to decay when there are no
photons present then adjust the k's with
the probability no will deal with the
coefficient one that's spontaneous
emission so spontaneous emission is the
emission which is unaffected by
additional particles because there are
no additional
articles spontaneous emission
stimulated emission is the tendency for
other particles to stimulate the
emission and have make it happen with a
higher probability there is a classical
analog of this incidentally um if you
have an atom which is radiating even
just classically and you have an
electromagnetic wave passing by it the
electromagnetic wave will vibrate the
will shake the electrons and cause them
to radiate with a higher probability
than they would have radiated or faster
radiate faster than they would have
radiated without that electromagnetic
wave going past and in fact it will tend
to make the emitted electromagnetic wave
come out with the same direction same
moment the same wave number so it really
is a quantum mechanical version of
something that was known classically
namely just that a pre-existing wave
will excite the system to to radiate
more just because pre-existing wave will
vibrate the electrons okay particles of
this type which have the tendency to
come out in the same state particles
that they don't really attract it's not
that they attract that so that would be
a wrong language but which have the
statistical probability because of the
square roots of n2 like to be in the
same state those are called bosons
they're characterized by creation and
annihilation operators let's write down
the mathematical rules
there's mathematical rules of bosons
for each momentum there are creation and
annihilation operators the creation and
annihilation operators have the property
that all creation operators for any
momenta commute so a + of K times a + of
L is the same thing as a plus of L times
a plus of K that's true if K equals L or
K bar or K doesn't equal L same thing
with the annihilation operators but an
annihilation operator with a creation
operator they do not commute now
remember what we found for the harmonic
oscillator when we did it just one
oscillator a - with a plus we got one
one alright this is one if K equals L
and 0 otherwise so the rule is they
always commute if we're talking about
different momenta if we're talking about
the same momenta than an annihilation
operator and a creation operator do not
commute but have a one on the right hand
side we can write that in the form Delta
K L where Delta KL is the Kronecker
Delta the symbol which is 1 if K equals
L and 0 otherwise this together Delta KL
together with the definition
the sigh of X is equal sum of I guess a
minus of K is it e to the plus or each
other - what could I have written I
think e to the minus ikx if I can
remember correctly with that definition
this basically defines the simplest
quantum field theory psy is a quantum
field and its job is to create and
annihilate particles one more one more
thing about bosons before we go on to
fermions fermions are kind of particle
which are different obviously otherwise
they wouldn't have another name one more
thing about bosons let's look at side
dagger of X sine of X integrated over
all space what is that object now I know
what that object is I wouldn't have
written it down if I didn't know what it
was but let's work it out let's pretend
we didn't know what it was and see if we
can work out what it is
sigh our quantum mechanical operators
this is an observable ok let's work it
out it's equal from the definition of sy
into the saw let's see some oh I think I
want R that's right sum of a plus of K
there it's each of our ikx I keep
getting confused about the pluses and
minuses I'll probably make mistakes
that's sigh of X at side dagger of X
what about sy of X
hmm oh it's a - Greta ah - it wouldn't
make any difference for this calculation
that's right the power and some balance
of yes it is it is it is okay so this is
some of a k then there's another one
which is sum over L which is the
annihilation operator a - of L e to the
plus I LX and this gets integrated over
X now let's see if we can examine what
that quantity is this is integral DX the
only X dependence here is in these
coefficient functions all right so what
we really need to know is what the
integral e to the I LX e to the i L
minus K X DX is that's the integral that
appears here e to the I LX e to the
minus ikx that's this integrated the X
that's the integration that appears here
what do we integrate we integrate over
all of space which means over this
circle of length L so what do we get if
we integrate this over a circle of my
well supposing first of all k is equal
to L naught 2 pi just L just their home
so you get L if K is equal to L what if
K is not equal to L it's 0 why because
it because this will be sines and
cosines and if you integrate a sine and
a cosine around the close around the you
know an integer multiple of wavelengths
you get 0 both sines and cosines are
positive as much as they are negative so
what is this thing this is Delta KL
times the length of the times the length
of the interval all right so that means
when we do this integral it's going to
pick out only the terms where K and L
are equal that's what this means it's
going to give us a factor of big L so it
gives us L times the sum over K but now
it's a single sum and not a double sum
because K has to be equal to L and
what's it going to be it's going to be a
plus of K a minus of K do you remember
for the harmonic oscillator with a plus
times a minus was the occupation number
a plus times a minus is the occupation
number is the number of quanta with
momentum K go back to your notes a plus
times a minus if you work out all the
square roots of ends and things a plus
times a minus acting on any state just
gives you the same thing as the
occupation number so a plus times a
minus is the occupation number the
number of particles with momentum K what
if you sum that over K
total number particles hey yeah let's
say it just counts the number of
particles total number of particles so
this object here if I divide it by L I
have to provide it by L because of this
L which appears here that is equal to
the number of particles total number of
particles now there are conventions
where you absorb this L into sy and
there's a more normal canal I have been
following a particular set of
conventions it's led me to have this one
over L out here that's alright we can
leave it there but basically size star
times I is accounting quantity it counts
the number of particles its observable
it's a quantum mechanical operator but
all it is is the number of particles
number of particles may or may not be
conserved so in general this integral
can change with time
if particles are absorbed in annihilator
are absorbed it all created on the other
hand if the number of particles was
conserved then this is a conserved
quantity so this is the thing which
counts the number of particles are apart
from this l would you give a name to sy
start on the sides are the Institut you
could call it the number of particles
appoint X but that's not such a good
idea because you know the density of
particles at X right so that's apart
from a factor of L which I will ignore
just uh
it'll go away when we play sums over
kaze by integrals over K but apart from
a factor K psystar psy let's just say
psystar psy is proportional to equals
the density of particles at X sorry sine
of X sine of X and it's a quantum
mechanical operator so that's it that is
the simplest of all quantum field
theories a boson ik quantum field theory
where the fields are made up out of
creation in both an i elation operators
there's a sigh there is a sighs star and
you can work out incidentally it's fun
to work out the commutation relations
between sigh of X and size star of X we
know the commutation relations of the
A's the sighs are built out of the A's
it's interesting to work out the
commutation relations of the size okay
so that the move on a little bit like I
got yellow that's the density of
particles of X now as I said this this
whole machinery so far assumes there is
one species of identical particles
identicals means they're all the same
kind they're identical except for the
fact that they might have different
momenta or different position but you
wouldn't want to build into a single
quantum field both electrons and photons
this might be the field for photons now
because because of relativity we have to
modify it a little bit this would not be
the field of electrons because electrons
are not bosons and they and they have to
be dealt with differently okay that's
that's a that's the basic theory of
bosons they are described by harmonic
oscillator creation and annihilation
operators
which are the Fourier coefficients of
the field they like the in some
statistical sense they'd like to come
out in the same state if they're already
particles present that will enhance the
rate of production of particles with the
same momentum and the creation and
annihilation operators have definite
algebraic properties commutation
relations which I've left listed here
that's it that's the whole theory of a
very simple quantum field again I
emphasize that you can use it to
describe reactions with particles are
created yeah everything's
one-dimensional now but that's the bad
this that can be immediately changes by
putting in more X's right there's
nothing special about that
I see people there are some people have
to go and I don't want to start a new
subject where are people going but
perhaps so we can spend a little while
talking about something dumb whatever
you want to talk about which is not not
a linear progression
oh I see
well transparency in the transparency is
simply interference you can have a thing
which is transparent to electrons you
can have a thing which is transparent to
okay so what are the things in nature of
bosons lots of things Higgs boson is a
boson the expose on the why well lots of
things are bosons gravitons of bosons
um I what is we say that sigh or sigh
dagger and so forth is an observable
that means that the field sigh is kind
of like the electromagnetic field you
can observe it you can do an experiment
and measure side when the sigh be hey
vly CAC lassika thing now there's a
problem about measuring sigh its
components don't commute with each other
it's real and imaginary parts don't
commute with each other and you can't
simultaneously measure two non commuting
things
alright so science i dagger don't
commute that means the real and
imaginary parts of side aren't commute
how can you measure sigh if the real and
imaginary parts don't commit and answer
is you can't
you cannot you also can't measure X and
P at the same time what is it or for
that matter the harmonic oscillator
variables a and a dagger or a even a you
can't measure because it has to none
commuting a real and imaginary part what
is the situation let's take the harmonic
oscillator first in which um the
harmonic oscillator variables behave
classically and an approximate sense you
can measure
both a and a dagger or for an ordinary
young well what was the situation when
the oscillator is highly excited when
the oscillator is highly excited and
that's the situation in which the number
of excitations a times a dagger is much
much larger than h-bar is much much
larger than the right hand side of the
commutation relations you can't
precisely measure these things
simultaneously but just in the same
sense that you can measure X and P
approximately as long as you don't
violate the uncertainty principle you
can measure the components of fields
approximately as long as you don't
violate certain uncertainty principles
well what is that in the practice mean
it in practice means that you can
measure these things as long as the
degree of excitation as long as the
field strengths are large by comparison
with the uncertainties large by
comparison with the obstruction and
measuring them both simultaneously what
does it mean in terms of photons it
means lots of photons right when that's
right when you have a sufficiently large
number of photons then approximately you
can measure the the different components
of the field simultaneously within
certain errors but those errors may be a
lot smaller than the magnitudes of the
fields themselves so the observable
quantum fields thought of as things that
you can measure sigh and so forth those
behave like classical fields when the
number of quanta is very large it makes
sense when the number of quanta is very
large the field sigh behaves as if it
were a classical wave field it's only
when the number of quanta is small
you see their discreteness and that's
when psy does not behave like a
classical field anymore okay so that's
the that's the setup psy has a quantum
mechanical operator which does behave
classically under certain conditions it
is a measurable quantity or at least
parts some components of it are
measurable and it can be approximately
measured all of its components
simultaneously as long as the number of
photons is much larger than the
uncertainties dictated by the
uncertainty principle this is an
uncertainty principle it tells you that
the components of a and a dagger the
real and imaginary parts can't be
simultaneously measured yeah here's the
point a times a dagger a dagger a is the
number of particles that means roughly
speaking the magnitude of a is like the
square root of the number of particles
as long as a is much bigger than the
right hand side here as long as a times
a dagger is much bigger than the right
hand side the right hand side can
largely be ignored for many purposes and
that's the situation where our a behaves
approximately classically okay any other
questions
yeah is that can the the industry in the
initial stage of the final state that
that you started with as long as as long
as the number of partners we change
you know if you go in the other
direction which is going you stand up
with a state of zero zero zero zero the
ground state that's a highly portable
state well supposing you apply a
destruction operator to that state yeah
I thought I heard you say that to forget
no state we got zero if we could get the
lowest state with no particles in it
again no state you have to distinguish
now good the state zero is a state with
no particles in it it is not the same as
the state zero all right this this label
this state is the ground state of a
harmonic oscillator it's norm is one
it's not the zero state the zero state
is OH - oh it's it's just this is just a
vector which I've labeled as oh it is
not the zero vector in a vector space
it's the vector describing no particles
that's different than the zero vector
very different very very different zero
vector is no vector at all it doesn't
describe anything ah this is a perfectly
good normalized vector describing no
particles for the ground States
it seems like there are two states one
or two kinds of states
what is the fear that's not a state
that's a that's an operator field is not
a state it's an operator today yeah in
quantum field theory fields or operators
okay so that's not a state and we have
something which is a safe way out
I'm not reality with regular model
periodic and try to apply it to the real
world like you can say that they can't
focus on the life size of the universe
but it's not very useful oh how do you
use it in practice like the size of
cavity or whether you use well a more
common situation is when you have a
cavity with reflecting walls okay so
that's a common situation but you could
imagine electrons moving around on a
wire on a closed wire that would be an
example
the L influence the number of possible
states together putting a limit on Jake
l yeah defines the number of possible
state putting a limit on Big L know it
doesn't know it doesn't it does it
doesn't put a limit on the number of
states what it says is that K the
allowable values of K have to be two PI
over L times n and n can be any integer
what it does is it limits the number of
states with momentum below a certain
momentum so if you were to say the
largest momentum I'll ever want to think
about is well as some large amount of
momentum I never want to allow more
momentum than that then this would limit
the number of states but as long as you
can have arbitrarily high momentum so
that n can be arbitrarily large it
doesn't limit the number of states where
we started to exit T and drive me
- that's right it will be over here we
have be struck with the A+ name -
religion your value K well that responds
to the X of P in our case okay good
the X and P are right that's the real
and imaginary parts of the field in
other words the field psy one piece of
it has a pluses and the other piece has
a minuses I use this equal just you know
what I mean all right if you add oh
sorry side that guy plus if you add side
to side dagger of course you get the
real part of sorry and that's a plus
plus a minus
that's like X or maybe it's like P that
some room feels the real and imaginary
parts are the two conjugate variables
and they're the two variables the real
and imaginary part are the two variables
which have a distinct uncertainty
relation between them so side plus side
dagger plus sign side dagger plus or
minus I are two distinct objects that
the real and the imaginary part of sorry
and they correspond to the X and P of
the oscillator that's a good question
and that is question for in theory we're
actually going to have an infinite
number loops representing three space in
reality is it's three dimensional space
or shorter space yeah right we're gonna
try to
yeah no no what will you do for
three-dimensional space let's start with
two-dimensional space okay for
two-dimensional space what you would
imagine the analog of the circle is the
Taurus the Taurus the Taurus you usually
think of the Taurus is it doughnut or
the surface of the doughnut but from a
measurement from mathematicians point of
view what a Taurus is is you take a
rectangle in space and you identify the
left edge with the right edge and the
bottom edge with the top edge you can
think of it as first cutting the torus
imagine cutting the torus like that of
course we're talking about the surface
of the torus whoo-hoo ask me yeah all
right so we take the surface of the
torus and we lay it out what happens if
we cut the torus through and sort of
open it up well we get a piece of a
cylinder right and now we cut it that
but we remember that this edge is to be
identified with that edge then we slice
it through here and open it up but
remember that the top edge has to be
identified with the bottom edge so a
torus is a rectangle in which we
remember that this point is the same as
this point this point is the same as
this point and for example if we were
talking about a classical particle a
classical particle which left the torus
over here would reappear over here it
will come here it will reappear down
here that's the same as a classical
particle just moving around on the torus
it's got two directions of periodicity
and for this object both components of
the momentum the X and the y components
of momentum would be quantized so that's
the way to think about a torus as a
rectangle with periodic identifications
or with identifications across the
and of course if we had a field we would
require the field at this position to be
the same as the field at this position
the field at that point to be the same
as a field that that's it Alberto is
asking young represents space if you
represent the outdoors in space
you represent space or the object of
space yeah we're talking about space but
the only reason for making it periodic
is to avoid questions of infinity and
and eventually will will will make the
space infinite by replacing sums by
integrals incidentally there's a notion
of a three-dimensional torus a
three-dimensional torus is just a cube
with identifications this point is
identified well you know you just
identified this face is identified with
that face the top is identified with the
bottom and the front is identified with
the back so Tauruses can tour I can
exist in any dimensions and the notion
of a periodic
particle moving in periodic space is
just the notion of a particle moving
within the interior of a cube but in
such a way that when it reaches the edge
of the torus or the Reg of the cube it
reappears at the opposite oxen and
bloomie goes goodbye
space into its periodic representation
is there one that ones you here we
haven't specified anything that
statistically ality is one chosen by
everybody when they go to winter one
what road is is a a quantum a true
physical quantum jozin one day you know
number Quantico quanta are the particles
cuantos I'll put the can change they
come and they go they're created or
annihilated they're radiated in size
well that of course is a very very
speculative question my own answer would
probably be no but I think you're you're
asking
probably questions about length scales
of plunky in size and so forth and ah
that's way beyond what we're talking
about here so most likely quantum field
theory just breaks down by the time you
get to such scales it just probably
doesn't make sense
so that's where we're talking about
situations
um of let's say modest length scales
scales of ten to the minus thirteen
centimeters ten to the minus xx
centimeter centimeters 10 to the minus
twenty eight centimeters but not 10 to
the minus 33 centimeters where that is
and so but the math itself abstracted is
just annoying
all right but you know for almost all
practical purposes the to take space to
be continuous rather than the screen
incidentally its momentum which was
discrete not space when we put things on
a circle
it was the momenta the k's which were
discrete not the positions of particles
positions of particles were periodic the
momenta was speed the more these people
because we curiosity but we assume the
wave function was periodic yep yeah but
it comes back to itself after yeah now
you can question that and in fact the is
legitimate to question it but in the
simplest quantum field theory
sparking commutation relation between
the knowledge the radio operator and
change it to prior to this - development
kale is that a simple throw neon theory
register if you replace commentators by
anti commutator so commutator of a and B
is a B - BAE
so yeah that's equal to the commutator
of a with B and it's anti-symmetric and
that if you interchange a and b it
changes sign the anti commutator is by
definition and it's usually written this
way a B it's a B plus B a now I save
this for last because it's harder to
swallow that a B doesn't be that a B
plus B a equals zero that's harder to
swallow than a B minus B a is equal to
zero here we have I mean here we have
almost everything is normal a plus times
a minus is the same as a - I'm sorry
eight plus times a plus is the same as a
plus times a plus in the opposite
direction it's only a small subset of
things which are odd okay if we were to
replace this by anti commutator 's
almost everything would be odd a B plus
BA would equal zero for almost all of
them all of the time so we'll come to
that but such mathematical manipulations
define fermions and fermions are exactly
the particles that have a poly exclusion
principle you simply can't put two of
them into this not only do they not like
to be in the same state they can't be in
the same state there there's a complete
opposite to the notion of stimulated
emission if you have a Fermi on in a box
and you try
create another one with the same
momentum or same everything you can't
you can only put one of them in the
state and that has to be reflected
somehow by the algebra of the creation
and annihilation operators there are
creation and annihilation operators for
fermions but they're such that the
algebra instead of telling you that
they'd like to come out in the same
state tells you they cannot come out in
the same state so that's a yeah and if
you can't put a lot of them in the same
state it never behaves classically our
goal is our main fermions it's weird if
you take two fermions you make a boson
you cannot put two fermions in the state
but if you make if you make a boson out
of two fermions you can put the tools
you can put two bosons in the same state
but that's not the same as putting the
fermions and it will not woo some kind
of reals
will we see eventually how to put in
like an external field yes I mean in
this right now there's no like an
external field back in here
we yeah he's all like three particles
right external fields can either be
described as classical external fields
or they can be described as large
numbers of quanta and that's a kind of
boundary condition that the effects of
large numbers of quanta should be in one
to be essentially the same within small
deviations from the effect of a
classical field that's of course how a
lot of this was deduced are saying well
somehow the electromagnetic field has to
describe discrete quanta but when
there's a lot of them it better reduce
to the right thing for more please visit
us at stanford.edu